<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2. Geometry on Thought Thou Art</title>
    <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2. Geometry on Thought Thou Art</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 19:38:35 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>2.1 Triangle Secrets</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/triangle-secrets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 19:38:45 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/triangle-secrets/</guid>
      <description>Geometry Sessions Geometry is a standard subject in regular high school Mathematics unlike Number Theory which is usually not covered in regular school curriculums. So, what we will do in these EC Math (Extra-curricular Math) sessions in Geometry will draw upon standard topics we learn in school and go beyond to find some very interesting results and discoveries.
Geometry is also one of the oldest fields of Mathematics, the other being the study of numbers or Arithmetic and Number Theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.3 About Parallelograms</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/parallelograms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 14:40:48 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/parallelograms/</guid>
      <description>As we expand from triangles into the world of quadrilaterals, one of the first few we encounter are of course the square and the rectangle. Parallelograms are not far behind, and hold many secrets, some of which we explore in this session.
Quadrilaterals  Defn 1: A quadrilateral is a planar figure with 4 sides (edges) and 4 corners (vertices).   Based on this definition, we can draw a few different kinds of quadrilaterals shown below:      The difference between simple quadrilaterals and complex quadrilaterals should be easy to note, it is whether we allow the edge crossings in the quadrilateral or not.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>