<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thought Thou Art</title>
    <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Thought Thou Art</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 07:08:58 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.thoughtart.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>1.1 Greatest Common Divisor</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/number-theory/gcd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 19:40:47 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/number-theory/gcd/</guid>
      <description>Multiplication Let’s start with the basics first. We have learnt since childhood that multiplication is simply repeated addition. For eg, 3 x 4 is really the “shorthand notation” for saying 3 + 3 + 3 + 3.
Where does multiplication show up practically, in real life? Suppose you have a room that is 3m wide and 4m long. How many 1m square tiles are needed to cover the room?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Binomial Theorem</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/binomial-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 20:58:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/binomial-theorem/</guid>
      <description>Basic Mathematical Operations We have come a long way as human beings exploring mathematical operations. We will take a quick refresher here before getting into the binomial theorem.
Addition We started of course with the addition operation, starting with the addition of natural numbers, like 3 and 2 as shown in the pic1 below:
 3 &amp;#43; 2 = 5   In pioneering research conducted by psychologist Karen Wynn in 1990s, she reported that five-month-old human infants are able to compute the outcomes of simple addition and subtraction operations on small sets of physical objects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sets</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/sets/</guid>
      <description>In a class of 20 children, 5 of them like History, 10 of them like English and 15 of them like Math!! Do you think this is an impossible statement, or is it possible to have class of only 20 children where all the conditions above are satisfied? What if we are posed an additional question - what is the maximum number of students who may not like any of these three subjects?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basics of Counting</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/basics-of-counting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 19:38:25 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/basics-of-counting/</guid>
      <description>Going to St Ives We start with a counting riddle in the form of an English-language nursery rhyme from the 1700s. The poem goes as follows:
 As I was going to St Ives,
Upon the road I met seven wives;
Every wife had seven sacks,
Every sack had seven cats,
Every cat had seven kits:
Kits, cats, sacks, and wives,
How many were going to St Ives?
 There are many ways to answer this question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequences and Series</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/sequences-and-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 07:08:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/sequences-and-series/</guid>
      <description>Why study sequences? Sequences have been interesting to humans for a long time because of the patterns they hide within them. Just the discovery of these patterns have given us immense joy. An added advantage of discovering and describing a pattern is the ability to predict the future. A classic example is the discovery of the pattern of the Halley&amp;rsquo;s comet, and the prediction of its next observation. Imagine the surprise and joy that would have accompanied when over 250 years ago, the comet was spotted as predicted by Edmund Halley in 1758.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Role of Repetition</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/counting-with-repetition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 18:05:19 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/counting-with-repetition/</guid>
      <description>Counting with Repetition Cracking the combination Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the total numbers that are there between 1 and 1000 (both inclusive). Even the youngest of kids would know that there are obviously 1000 numbers in this range. Let&amp;rsquo;s just shift the start and the end a little and ask - how many numbers are there between 0 and 999 (both inclusive), the answer is again 1000 numbers.
Now lets consider this same counting problem in a different scenario.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factorial</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/factorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 01:26:59 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/factorial/</guid>
      <description>St Ives revisted Here is a new version of the St Ives poem:
 As I was going to St Ives,
Upon the road I met 2 wives;
Every wife had 3 sacks,
Every sack had 4 cats,
Every cat had 5 kits,
I am not playing any tricks,
Just count and tell me the number of kits.
 Counting the number of kittens is similar to before except that the numbers involved here are a little different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic Progression</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/arithmetic-progression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 20:59:08 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/arithmetic-progression/</guid>
      <description>AP basics  Defn 1: An Arithmetic Progression (or an AP) is a sequence of numbers such that the difference between consecutive terms is a constant.   Examples Here are a few examples of APs:
 The sequence of odd natural numbers which is simply - \( (1, 3, 5, 7, 9, \ldots ) \) - is an AP, because the difference between any two consecutive terms is \(2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Progression</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/geometric-progression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 20:59:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/geometric-progression/</guid>
      <description>GP basics  Defn 1: A Geometric Progression (or a GP) is a sequence of numbers such that the ratio between consecutive terms is a constant.   Note that the constant can be a positive natural number (such as 10), or a fractional number (such as 1&amp;frasl;2 or 0.25, etc), or even a negative number (such as -2).
Examples Here are a few examples of APs:
 The sequence of powers of two which is simply - \( (1, 2, 4, 8, 16, \ldots ) \) - is a GP, because the ratio between any two consecutive terms is \(2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Permutations</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/permutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 19:38:34 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/permutations/</guid>
      <description>We have had a glimpse of counting problems, and looked at two fundamental principles of counting - namely the product rule and the sum rule. We now take next steps in exploring more kinds of counting problems. This session on Permutations and the next one on Combinations are the basic kinds of counting problems commonly studied.
Arrangements of n-items School Championship Suppose you have 3 houses in your school for the Sports Championship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combinations</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/combinations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 19:38:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/combinations/</guid>
      <description>In this session, we are interested in a slightly different class of counting problems, where the order of the items does not matter.
Choosing without order Student Volunteers Suppose, we have 5 students with us, and we want 2 volunteers from these 5 students in order to do something. How many ways in which we can have 2 volunteers from these 5 students?
Note the key difference compared to the other kind of problem we have looked at - suppose 5 students were running a race, and we were interested in how many was can the top-2 positions be filled?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/ec-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 10:57:27 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/ec-problems/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.1 Triangle Secrets</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/triangle-secrets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 19:38:45 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/triangle-secrets/</guid>
      <description>Geometry Sessions Geometry is a standard subject in regular high school Mathematics unlike Number Theory which is usually not covered in regular school curriculums. So, what we will do in these EC Math (Extra-curricular Math) sessions in Geometry will draw upon standard topics we learn in school and go beyond to find some very interesting results and discoveries.
Geometry is also one of the oldest fields of Mathematics, the other being the study of numbers or Arithmetic and Number Theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory Sheet</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/p3-math/revision/memory-sheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 08:34:21 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/p3-math/revision/memory-sheet/</guid>
      <description>Algebra Modulus There are 2 kinds of problems typically asked in the Modulus topic.
Equality problems
Where the problem involves an equality with a modulus, either on one side or both sides of the equation, simply resolve the modulus by using the \( \pm \) sign. For e.g., to solve,
$$ \begin{array}{rcl} |2x + 1| &amp; = &amp; |x + 5| \\ \therefore 2x + 1 &amp; = &amp; \pm (x + 5) \\ \therefore 2x + 1 = x + 5 &amp; OR &amp; 2x + 1 = -(x + 5) \\ \end{array} $$ Inequality problems</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.2 PRIME-ing up, for PERFECT-ion - TBD</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/number-theory/primeing-up-for-perfection/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 21:32:29 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/number-theory/primeing-up-for-perfection/</guid>
      <description>Notes TBD</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S9</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/c1/t5/s9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 19:26:07 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/c1/t5/s9/</guid>
      <description>Cslides</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S8</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/c1/t5/s8/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 19:26:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/c1/t5/s8/</guid>
      <description>Cslides</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>N1</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/c1/t5/n1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 19:25:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/c1/t5/n1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Lorem markdownum, a quoque nutu est quodcumque mandasset veluti. Passim inportuna totidemque nympha fert; repetens pendent, poenarum guttura sed vacet non, mortali undas. Omnis pharetramque gramen portentificisque membris servatum novabis fallit de nubibus atque silvas mihi. Dixit repetitaque Quid; verrit longa; sententia mandat quascumque nescio solebat litore; noctes. Hostem haerentem circuit plenaque tamen.
 Pedum ne indigenae finire invergens carpebat Velit posses summoque De fumos illa foret  Est simul fameque tauri qua ad Locum nullus nisi vomentes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/about/</guid>
      <description>We are a small group of education enthusiasts. We believe that education should be freely and widely available. We like to see Math and Science and such topics explained in simple ways so that larger and larger audience can enjoy the beauty of the discoveries in these areas. The same holds true with the inventions in the areas of Engineering and Technology, although with sufficient care. Together, we would like to see STEM take greater roots in the mindshare of young ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/contact/</guid>
      <description> Your Name Your Email* Message   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Follow</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/follow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/follow/</guid>
      <description>Social page</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/terms/</guid>
      <description>Everything on this website is free for use. Especially for academic usage. If you plan to use the material for commercial purposes, that is free too. Except, include a reference to this website as a source, and you need to share alike.
So, everything under CC (Creative Commons), BY (meaning provide attribution), SA (meaning Share derivatives of the work Alike) license, more formally:
 
Everything on this website by Thought Thou Art is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>