<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thought Thou Art</title>
    <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Thought Thou Art</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 08:50:14 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.thoughtart.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Growth</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/exponential-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 19:40:20 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/exponential-growth/</guid>
      <description>We explored the Laws of Indices and Surds in a previous session. Lets take that one step further by exploring exponentials before venturing into Logarithms.
You may have heard this puzzle in your childhood - there is a pond with a lotus plant growing. On the first day, one lotus flower blooms from the plant. On the second day, there are two flowers. On the third day, there are four flowers and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sizing Up Numbers</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/sizing-up-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 11:08:03 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/sizing-up-numbers/</guid>
      <description>Big Numbers In a previous session we encountered this puzzle of an author on the way to St Ives, when he sees 7 wives on the way, each carrying 7 sacks, each with 7 cats, each with 7 kittens. And we found that the total number of kittens were 7 x 7 x 7 x 7 = 2401 kittens. Those many kittens would be hard to manage, but the number itself easily manageable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basics</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 21:49:46 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/basics/</guid>
      <description>We have looked at linear functions, \( f(x) = ax + b \), quadratic functions of the form \( f(x) = ax^2 + bx + c \), and even cubic functions of the form \( f(x) = ax^3 + bx^2 + cx + d \). All these functions belong to a class of functions commonly known as polynomials. It should be easy to guess that a quartic function would follow the cubic function in the same pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quadratics - TBD</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions-and-solutions/quadratics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 14:48:37 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions-and-solutions/quadratics/</guid>
      <description>Minimum and Maximum values Problem 1  Problem ↕  Find the minimum and maximum values of the function $$ y = 2x^2 - 4x+ 5 $$     Algebraic Solution ...  $$ \begin{array}{rcl} y &amp; = &amp; 2x^2 - 4x+ 5 \\ \\ y &amp; = &amp; 2(x^2 - 2x) + 5 \\ \\ \therefore y &amp; = &amp; 2(x^2 - 2x + 1) + 3 \\ &amp; &amp; \text{Completing the square here}\\ \\ \therefore y &amp; = &amp; 2(x - 1)^2 + 3 \\ \end{array} $$     Answer ↕  Minimum value = 3, maximum value = \( \infty \), i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.1 Triangle Secrets</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/triangle-secrets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 19:38:45 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/triangle-secrets/</guid>
      <description>Geometry Sessions Geometry is a standard subject in regular high school Mathematics unlike Number Theory which is usually not covered in regular school curriculums. So, what we will do in these EC Math (Extra-curricular Math) sessions in Geometry will draw upon standard topics we learn in school and go beyond to find some very interesting results and discoveries.
Geometry is also one of the oldest fields of Mathematics, the other being the study of numbers or Arithmetic and Number Theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.1 Greatest Common Divisor</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/number-theory/gcd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 19:40:47 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/number-theory/gcd/</guid>
      <description>Multiplication Let’s start with the basics first. We have learnt since childhood that multiplication is simply repeated addition. For eg, 3 x 4 is really the “shorthand notation” for saying 3 + 3 + 3 + 3.
Where does multiplication show up practically, in real life? Suppose you have a room that is 3m wide and 4m long. How many 1m square tiles are needed to cover the room?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Binomial Theorem</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/binomial-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 20:58:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/binomial-theorem/</guid>
      <description>Basic Mathematical Operations We have come a long way as human beings exploring mathematical operations. We will take a quick refresher here before getting into the binomial theorem.
Addition We started of course with the addition operation, starting with the addition of natural numbers, like 3 and 2 as shown in the pic1 below:
 3 &amp;#43; 2 = 5   In pioneering research conducted by psychologist Karen Wynn in 1990s, she reported that five-month-old human infants are able to compute the outcomes of simple addition and subtraction operations on small sets of physical objects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sets</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/sets/</guid>
      <description>In a class of 20 learners, 5 of them have taken History, 10 of them have taken English and 15 of them have taken Math!! Do you think this is an impossible statement, or is it possible to have class of only 20 learners where all the conditions above are satisfied? What if we are posed an additional question - what is the maximum number of learners who may not have taken any of these three subjects?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basics of Counting</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/basics-of-counting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 19:38:25 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/basics-of-counting/</guid>
      <description>Going to St Ives We start with a counting riddle in the form of an English-language nursery rhyme from the 1700s. The poem goes as follows:
 As I was going to St Ives,
Upon the road I met seven wives;
Every wife had seven sacks,
Every sack had seven cats,
Every cat had seven kits:
Kits, cats, sacks, and wives,
How many were going to St Ives?
 There are many ways to answer this question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Growth Rates</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/comparing-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 09:24:30 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/comparing-growth/</guid>
      <description>To understand the different kinds of growth rates, lets put them next to each other and compare.
Graphs of functions Linear Functions You have learnt about linear functions in earlier Math classes and they take the following form: $$ f(x) = a\cdot x + b $$ Or the more popular form of \( y = mx + c \). For the sake of the comparison, lets make the constant term 0, and plot linear functions for different values of the slope \( m\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laws of Indices</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/laws-of-indices/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 15:11:27 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/laws-of-indices/</guid>
      <description>First lets revisit the definition of exponentiation:
 Defn: Exponentiation is simply repeated application of multiplication. Given a postive number \(a\) and a positive integer \(m\), we define \(a^m\) (pronounced &amp;ldquo;a power m&amp;rdquo;) simply as:
$$ a^m = \underbrace{a \times a \times a \times \cdots \times a}_{m\text{ times}} $$
   Note that we are starting with both \( a \) and \( m \) as positive integers. As we go along, we will expand the realm of applicability of the exponentiation operation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Construction</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/constructing-polynomials/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 10:33:45 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/constructing-polynomials/</guid>
      <description>EC Note - This topic is not in the syllabus of IGCSE Additional Mathematics curriculum, its an ExtraCurricular topic. But is an interesting topic nevertheless that learners can explore if interested.
While finding the roots of a polynomial is an involved activity, doing the opposite turns out to be fairly simple. If we are given the roots of a polynomial, can we construct the polynomial back from it?
To keep it simple, we will restrict ourselves to real rools, and in fact to polynomials for whome all the roots of the polynomial are real.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequences and Series</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/sequences-and-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 07:08:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/sequences-and-series/</guid>
      <description>Why study sequences? Sequences have been interesting to humans for a long time because of the patterns they hide within them. Just the discovery of these patterns have given us immense joy. An added advantage of discovering and describing a pattern is the ability to predict the future. A classic example is the discovery of the pattern of the Halley&amp;rsquo;s comet, and the prediction of its next observation. Imagine the surprise and joy that would have accompanied when over 250 years ago, the comet was spotted as predicted by Edmund Halley in 1758.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Role of Repetition</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/counting-with-repetition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 18:05:19 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/counting-with-repetition/</guid>
      <description>Counting with Repetition Cracking the combination Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the total numbers that are there between 1 and 1000 (both inclusive). Even the youngest of kids would know that there are obviously 1000 numbers in this range. Let&amp;rsquo;s just shift the start and the end a little and ask - how many numbers are there between 0 and 999 (both inclusive), the answer is again 1000 numbers.
Now lets consider this same counting problem in a different scenario.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mappings</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/mappings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/mappings/</guid>
      <description>Definition Now that we have looked at sets in fair amount of detail, we can start doing some interesting math when we take two sets and start relating the elements in one set to the elements in the other.
 Defn 1: A Mapping is simply a rule that connects elements of one set to the elements of another set.   Note that implicit in the defintion is notion of a first set whose elements are connected or mapped to the elements on the other set, the second set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Decay</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/exponential-decay/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 09:12:38 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/exponential-decay/</guid>
      <description>We have looked at exponentials to see how they aid the handling of large numbers. In that same session we also saw how exponentials aid in the study of very small numbers. Similarly, just like we saw exponential growth functions taking on very large values, we now look at exponential decay functions.
Coffee gets cold Ever wondered how your favorite hot drink gets cold? Imagine you made yourself a hot cup of coffee or a hot chocolate and got back to your desk to read up your mails while sipping on your drink.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exponents at Work</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/exponents-at-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 19:57:41 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/exponents-at-work/</guid>
      <description>Very large numbers Lets see how the notation for exponentiation and the laws of indices can be used to effectively manage large numbers. Recall the story of Reoh, our hero, who was on the maiden human flight to Andromeda Galaxy.
Suppose he has to estimate the size of the Milky Way Galaxy from the following:
 The distance from the Sun to the nearest star, Alpha Centauri, is 40,000,000,000,000 kms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Arithmetic</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/polynomial-arithmetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 06:22:01 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/polynomial-arithmetic/</guid>
      <description>In this session, we will explore basic arithmetic operations that can be performed with polynomials, typically taking two of them together, but it can also be many.
Addition and Subtraction Addition and subtraction are the most basic operations that can be defined on two polynomials. Today, it may seem straighforward for us to define these operations. But when initially defined, it is likely it would have taken some amount of rigor to define it meaningfully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.3 About Parallelograms</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/parallelograms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 14:40:48 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/geometry/parallelograms/</guid>
      <description>As we expand from triangles into the world of quadrilaterals, one of the first few we encounter are of course the square and the rectangle. Parallelograms are not far behind, and hold many secrets, some of which we explore in this session.
Quadrilaterals  Defn 1: A quadrilateral is a planar figure with 4 sides (edges) and 4 corners (vertices).   Based on this definition, we can draw a few different kinds of quadrilaterals shown below:      The difference between simple quadrilaterals and complex quadrilaterals should be easy to note, it is whether we allow the edge crossings in the quadrilateral or not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factorial</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/factorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 01:26:59 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/factorial/</guid>
      <description>St Ives revisted Here is a new version of the St Ives poem:
 As I was going to St Ives,
Upon the road I met 2 wives;
Every wife had 3 sacks,
Every sack had 4 cats,
Every cat had 5 kits,
I am not playing any tricks,
Just count and tell me the number of kits.
 Counting the number of kittens is similar to before except that the numbers involved here are a little different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic Progression</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/arithmetic-progression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 20:59:08 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/arithmetic-progression/</guid>
      <description>AP basics  Defn 1: An Arithmetic Progression (or an AP) is a sequence of numbers such that the difference between consecutive terms is a constant.   Examples Here are a few examples of APs:
 The sequence of odd natural numbers which is simply - \( (1, 3, 5, 7, 9, \ldots ) \) - is an AP, because the difference between any two consecutive terms is \(2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functions</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/functions/</guid>
      <description>We have now covered all the background needed to delve into one of the most fundamental topics of Mathematics - we are now ready to understand what functions are. Almost every other session we do in the course of Additional Mathematics will build on this topic, so it is essential that you go through all the background we covered so far (that on Sets and Mappings and carefully understand the concept of functions described in great detail here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Logarithm Basics</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/logarithm-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 08:50:14 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/logarithm-basics/</guid>
      <description>Having explored exponentials in great detail, we are now in a position to explore the world of Logarithms.
Lets begin with the definition.
 Defn 1: The logarithm of a given number \( x\) to a fixed number called a base, say \(b\), is the exponent to which the fixed number \( b\) must be raised to produce the given number \(x\), i.e.
$$ y = \log_b (x) \iff x = b^y $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surds</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/working-with-surds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 21:07:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/indices-and-surds/working-with-surds/</guid>
      <description>Working with Surds Most textbook chapters on Surds cover the regular problems using the rules that pertain to addition, subtraction, mulitplication and division of surds, and of course, the most common of them all, rationalizing the denominator. We will only briefly touch upon these here, before moving on to some more interesting learnings on surds:
 Addition/Subtraction of surds:  When an integer and a surd are added/subtracted, there is no more simplifcation possible: $$2 \pm \sqrt{3}$$ When two different surds are added/subtracted, there is no more simplifcation possible: $$ \sqrt{2} + \sqrt{3}$$ When two similar surds are added/subtracted, the result cab be simplified as follows: $$ \sqrt{5} + 3\sqrt{5} = 4\sqrt{5}$$ $$ \sqrt[3]{5} - 4\sqrt[3]{5} = -3\sqrt[3]{5}$$  Multiplication/Division of surds:  When an integer and a surd are multiplied/divided, there is no more simplifcation possible: $$2 \sqrt{3} \text{ , } \frac{\sqrt{5}}{4}$$ When two surds of the same n-th root but different bases are multiplied/divided, the result can be simplified as follows: $$ \sqrt{2} \sqrt{3} = \sqrt{2\cdot 3} = \sqrt{6} $$ $$ \frac{\sqrt[3]{10}}{\sqrt[3]{5}} = \sqrt[3]{\frac{10}{5}} = \sqrt[3]{2}$$ When two surds of different n-th root but same base are multiplied/divided, the result can be simplified using the laws of indices: $$ \sqrt[3]{2} \sqrt{2} = 2^{\frac{1}{3}}2^{\frac{1}{2}} = 2^{\frac{1}{3} + \frac{1}{2}} = 2^{\frac{5}{6}} = \sqrt[6]{2^5}$$ $$ \frac{\sqrt[3]{10}}{\sqrt[4]{10}} = \frac{10^{\frac{1}{3}}}{10^\frac{1}{4}} = 10^{\frac{1}{3} - \frac{1}{4}} = 10^{\frac{1}{12}} = \sqrt[12]{10}$$ When two similar surds are multiplied/divided, the result can be simplified as follows: $$ \sqrt{5} \cdot 3\sqrt{5} = 3\cdot{5} = 15$$ $$ \sqrt[3]{5} \div 4\sqrt[3]{5} = \frac{1}{4}$$  Rationalizing the denominator:  When a surd occurs in the denominator, the usual practice is to rationalize the denominator and move the surd to the numerator as follows: $$ \frac{\sqrt{3}}{\sqrt{2}} = \frac{\sqrt{3}\cdot\sqrt{2}}{\sqrt{2}\cdot\sqrt{2}} = \frac{\sqrt{3}\cdot\sqrt{2}}{2} = \frac{\sqrt{6}}{2} $$ Or as follows (the surds \(3 - \sqrt{2}\) and \( 3 + \sqrt{2} \) are called conjugates of each other): $$ \frac{1}{3 + \sqrt{2}} = \frac{1\cdot(3 - \sqrt{2})}{(3 + \sqrt{2})\cdot(3 - \sqrt{2})} = \frac{3 - \sqrt{2}}{3^2 - (\sqrt{2})^2} = \frac{3 - \sqrt{2}}{9 - 2} = \frac{3 - \sqrt{2}}{7} $$  A combination of operations:  An example with all of the above opertations is as follows: $$ \begin{array}{rcl} \displaystyle \frac{(1 + \sqrt{5})^2}{\sqrt{3} - 1} &amp; = &amp; \displaystyle \frac{1 + 2\sqrt{5} + (\sqrt{5})^2}{\sqrt{3} - 1} \\ \\ &amp; = &amp; \displaystyle \frac{6 + 2\sqrt{5}}{\sqrt{3} - 1} \\ \\ &amp; = &amp; \displaystyle \frac{2\cdot(3 + \sqrt{5})\cdot(\sqrt{3} + 1)}{(\sqrt{3} - 1)\cdot(\sqrt{3} + 1)} \\ \\ &amp; = &amp; \displaystyle \frac{2\cdot(3 + \sqrt{5})\cdot(\sqrt{3} + 1)}{(\sqrt{3})^2 - 1^2} \\ \\ &amp; = &amp; \displaystyle \frac{2\cdot(3 + \sqrt{5})\cdot(\sqrt{3} + 1)}{3 - 1} \\ \\ &amp; = &amp; \displaystyle \frac{\cancel{2}\cdot(3 + \sqrt{5})\cdot(\sqrt{3} + 1)}{\cancel{2}} \\ \\ &amp; = &amp; 3\sqrt{3} + \sqrt{5}\cdot\sqrt{3} + 3 + \sqrt{5}\\ \\ \therefore \displaystyle \frac{(1 + \sqrt{5})^2}{\sqrt{3} - 1} &amp; = &amp; 3 + 3\sqrt{3} + \sqrt{5} + \sqrt{15} \\ \end{array} $$    We will stop here with these purely algebraic manipulations of surds and look at some interesting ideas around them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 20:50:42 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Progression</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/geometric-progression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 20:59:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/series/geometric-progression/</guid>
      <description>GP basics  Defn 1: A Geometric Progression (or a GP) is a sequence of numbers such that the ratio between consecutive terms is a constant.   Note that the constant can be a positive natural number (such as 10), or a fractional number (such as 1&amp;frasl;2 or 0.25, etc), or even a negative number (such as -2).
Examples Here are a few examples of APs:
 The sequence of powers of two which is simply - \( (1, 2, 4, 8, 16, \ldots ) \) - is a GP, because the ratio between any two consecutive terms is \(2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Permutations</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/permutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 19:38:34 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/permutations/</guid>
      <description>We have had a glimpse of counting problems, and looked at two fundamental principles of counting - namely the product rule and the sum rule. We now take next steps in exploring more kinds of counting problems. This session on Permutations and the next one on Combinations are the basic kinds of counting problems commonly studied.
Arrangements of n-items School Championship Suppose you have 3 houses in your school for the Sports Championship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laws of Logarithms</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/laws-of-logarithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 12:27:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/logarithms/laws-of-logarithms/</guid>
      <description>TBD</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Composite Functions</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/composite-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 23:21:46 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/composite-functions/</guid>
      <description>It is worth taking a little pause here to note that we started with a very basic definition of sets, just as a collection of objects and from there on started building more and more ideas purely with our imagination. Composite function is yet another such idea. First, we put one set in front of another and made the definitions of mappings and functions. Now, we put one function in front of another and ask the question what would happen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combinations</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/combinations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 19:38:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/combinations/</guid>
      <description>In this session, we are interested in a slightly different class of counting problems, where the order of the items does not matter.
Choosing without order Student Volunteers Suppose, we have 5 students with us, and we want 2 volunteers from these 5 students in order to do something. How many ways in which we can have 2 volunteers from these 5 students?
Note the key difference compared to the other kind of problem we have looked at - suppose 5 students were running a race, and we were interested in how many was can the top-2 positions be filled?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Function</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/inverse-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:12:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/inverse-function/</guid>
      <description>In very simple terms, the inverse of a function is one that reverses what the function does. For e.g., if the function maps 2.3 to say 41, then the inverse should map 41 to 2.3.
 An example function f      And its inverse function     For a function to have an inverse it should be bijective, which means it should be both injective and surjective:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Graphs</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/exploring-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 20:04:09 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/exploring-graphs/</guid>
      <description>In this session, we will explore graphs of functions in more detail. It usually helps to visualize the graph of a function, how it looks in the Cartesian co-ordinate system along with the algebraic definition of the function.
Linear Function Lets&amp;rsquo;s first start with a very simple linear function, given as follows: $$ f : \R \to \R \text{ such that } f(x) = 2x $$
The graph of this function is shown below:   The graph of a linear function passing through the origin      The part of the function in the interval of the domain \( [-1, 2] \) is depicted as a solid line and the rest of the graph is shown with dotted lines just for ease of visualization and to avoid congestion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/ec-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 10:57:27 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/combinatorics/ec-problems/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modulus Function</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/modulus-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 04:05:01 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/modulus-function/</guid>
      <description>Defn 1: The modulus function \(f(x) = |x| \) is defined as follows:
$$ \displaystyle |x| = \left\{{\begin{array}{rl} x, &amp; {\text{if }}x0\\ 0, &amp; {\text{if }}x=0\\ -x, &amp; {\text{if }}x  This can be depicted graphically as shown below:   The graph of the modulus function      Another way to look at the above modulus function is to look at the graph of the function \( y = x\) and wherever the graph is going below the x-axis, flip it vertically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/practice-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 05:12:13 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/practice-problems/</guid>
      <description>These problems are from past exams of IGCSE Add Math papers, borrowed from the Cambridge University Press coursebook.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions-and-solutions/practice-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 20:48:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions-and-solutions/practice-problems/</guid>
      <description>A. Range of a quadratic The quadratic functions below are all defined over the domain \( \R \) and co-domain \( \R \). Do the following for each of them:
a. Express the quadratic function in the form \( y = a(x - h)^2 + k \).
b. Plot a rough sketch graph of the function, make sure to mark the point where the graph attains a maximum / minimum value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Problems #2</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 04:51:22 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems-2/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2.3 Parallelograms</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/ec-problems/parallelograms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 01:06:41 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/ec-problems/parallelograms/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory Sheet</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/p3-math/revision/memory-sheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 08:34:21 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/p3-math/revision/memory-sheet/</guid>
      <description>Algebra Modulus There are 2 kinds of problems typically asked in the Modulus topic.
Equality problems
Where the problem involves an equality with a modulus, either on one side or both sides of the equation, simply resolve the modulus by using the \( \pm \) sign. For e.g., to solve,
$$ \begin{array}{rcl} |2x + 1| &amp; = &amp; |x + 5| \\ \therefore 2x + 1 &amp; = &amp; \pm (x + 5) \\ \therefore 2x + 1 = x + 5 &amp; OR &amp; 2x + 1 = -(x + 5) \\ \end{array} $$ Inequality problems</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>N1</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/t5/n1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 19:25:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/ec-math/t5/n1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Lorem markdownum, a quoque nutu est quodcumque mandasset veluti. Passim inportuna totidemque nympha fert; repetens pendent, poenarum guttura sed vacet non, mortali undas. Omnis pharetramque gramen portentificisque membris servatum novabis fallit de nubibus atque silvas mihi. Dixit repetitaque Quid; verrit longa; sententia mandat quascumque nescio solebat litore; noctes. Hostem haerentem circuit plenaque tamen.
 Pedum ne indigenae finire invergens carpebat Velit posses summoque De fumos illa foret  Est simul fameque tauri qua ad Locum nullus nisi vomentes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/about/</guid>
      <description>We are a small group of education enthusiasts. We believe that education should be freely and widely available. We like to see Math and Science and such topics explained in simple ways so that larger and larger audience can enjoy the beauty of the discoveries in these areas. The same holds true with the inventions in the areas of Engineering and Technology, although with sufficient care. Together, we would like to see STEM fields take greater roots in the mindshare of young ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/contact/</guid>
      <description> #mc_embed_signup{background:#fff; margin: auto; clear:left; width:400px;} .label{margin-left: 1em;} .bottom-margin{margin-bottom: 1.5em;} #mc_embed_signup .bg-black{background-color: #333;}  * indicates required Email Address *   First Name   Last Name   A little about yourself Learner Teacher / Parent Just interested           </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Follow</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/follow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/follow/</guid>
      <description>twitter icon    facebook icon      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/terms/</guid>
      <description>Everything on this website is free for use. Especially for academic usage. If you plan to use the material for commercial purposes, that is free too. Except, include a reference to this website as a source, and you need to share alike.
So, everything under CC (Creative Commons), BY (meaning provide attribution), SA (meaning Share derivatives of the work Alike) license, more formally:
 
Everything on this website by Thought Thou Art is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>