<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>5. Polynomials on Thought Thou Art</title>
    <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 5. Polynomials on Thought Thou Art</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 21:48:57 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Basics</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 21:49:46 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/basics/</guid>
      <description>We have looked at linear functions, \( f(x) = ax + b \), quadratic functions of the form \( f(x) = ax^2 + bx + c \), and even cubic functions of the form \( f(x) = ax^3 + bx^2 + cx + d \). All these functions belong to a class of functions commonly known as polynomials. It should be easy to guess that a quartic function would follow the cubic function in the same pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Construction</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/constructing-polynomials/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 10:33:45 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/constructing-polynomials/</guid>
      <description>Note - This topic is not in the syllabus of IGCSE Additional Mathematics curriculum. But is an interesting topic nevertheless that learners can explore if interested.
While finding the roots of a polynomial is an involved activity, doing the opposite turns out to be fairly simple. If we are given the roots of a polynomial, can we construct the polynomial back from it?
To keep it simple, we will restrict ourselves to real rools, and in fact to polynomials for whome all the roots of the polynomial are real.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial Arithmetic</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/polynomial-arithmetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 06:22:01 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/polynomials/polynomial-arithmetic/</guid>
      <description>In this session, we will explore basic arithmetic operations that can be performed with polynomials, typically taking two of them together, but it can also be many.
Addition and Subtraction Addition and subtraction are the most basic operations that can be defined on two polynomials. Today, it may seem straighforward for us to define these operations. But when initially defined, it is likely it would have taken some amount of rigor to define it meaningfully.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>