<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1. Functions on Thought Thou Art</title>
    <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 1. Functions on Thought Thou Art</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:56:52 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sets</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/sets/</guid>
      <description>In a class of 20 learners, 5 of them have taken History, 10 of them have taken English and 15 of them have taken Math!! Do you think this is an impossible statement, or is it possible to have class of only 20 learners where all the conditions above are satisfied? What if we are posed an additional question - what is the maximum number of learners who may not have taken any of these three subjects?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mappings</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/mappings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/mappings/</guid>
      <description>Definition Now that we have looked at sets in fair amount of detail, we can start doing some interesting math when we take two sets and start relating the elements in one set to the elements in the other.
 Defn 1: A Mapping is simply a rule that connects elements of one set to the elements of another set.   Note that implicit in the defintion is notion of a first set whose elements are connected or mapped to the elements on the other set, the second set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functions</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 06:57:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/functions/</guid>
      <description>We have now covered all the background needed to delve into one of the most fundamental topics of Mathematics - we are now ready to understand what functions are. Almost every other session we do in the course of Additional Mathematics will build on this topic, so it is essential that you go through all the background we covered so far (that on Sets and Mappings and carefully understand the concept of functions described in great detail here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 20:50:42 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Composite Functions</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/composite-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 23:21:46 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/composite-functions/</guid>
      <description>It is worth taking a little pause here to note that we started with a very basic definition of sets, just as a collection of objects and from there on started building more and more ideas purely with our imagination. Composite function is yet another such idea. First, we put one set in front of another and made the definitions of mappings and functions. Now, we put one function in front of another and ask the question what would happen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Function</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/inverse-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 00:12:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/inverse-function/</guid>
      <description>In very simple terms, the inverse of a function is one that reverses what the function does. For e.g., if the function maps 2.3 to say 41, then the inverse should map 41 to 2.3.
 An example function f      And its inverse function     For a function to have an inverse it should be bijective, which means it should be both injective and surjective:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Graphs</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/exploring-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 20:04:09 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/exploring-graphs/</guid>
      <description>In this session, we will explore graphs of functions in more detail. It usually helps to visualize the graph of a function, how it looks in the Cartesian co-ordinate system along with the algebraic definition of the function.
Linear Function Lets&amp;rsquo;s first start with a very simple linear function, given as follows: $$ f : \R \to \R \text{ such that } f(x) = 2x $$
The graph of this function is shown below:   The graph of a linear function passing through the origin      The part of the function in the interval of the domain \( [-1, 2] \) is depicted as a solid line and the rest of the graph is shown with dotted lines just for ease of visualization and to avoid congestion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modulus Function</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/modulus-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 04:05:01 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/modulus-function/</guid>
      <description>Defn 1: The modulus function \(f(x) = |x| \) is defined as follows:
$$ \displaystyle |x| = \left\{{\begin{array}{rl} x, &amp; {\text{if }}x0\\ 0, &amp; {\text{if }}x=0\\ -x, &amp; {\text{if }}x  This can be depicted graphically as shown below:   The graph of the modulus function      Another way to look at the above modulus function is to look at the graph of the function \( y = x\) and wherever the graph is going below the x-axis, flip it vertically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Problems</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/practice-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 05:12:13 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/practice-problems/</guid>
      <description>These problems are from past exams of IGCSE Add Math papers, borrowed from the Cambridge University Press coursebook.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Problems #2</title>
      <link>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 04:51:22 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.thoughtart.in/courses/add-math/functions/ec-problems-2/</guid>
      <description>EC problems may not always be easy problems. They are actually extra-curricular problems.. :) They usually add some interesting facets to the topic under discussion, some fascinating discoveries, etc. But they are usually not from the board syllabus for the topic. (As always, once you read a problem, take some time to attempt it yourself, if you need help, take a peek at the &amp;ldquo;Hint&amp;rdquo; section, then again attempt to solve it yourself, feel free to check the &amp;ldquo;Answer&amp;rdquo; section if you want to check the answer you found, or even just get a feel for the magnitude of the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>